A Guide to the Charles City County (Va.) Records, 1641-1901
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Charles City County (Va.) Records, 1641-1901
The Library of Virginia
1044738, 1044747, 1044758, 1044762, 1044772, 1044773, 1044806-1044811, 1044818, 1134631
14 boxes and/or volumes
Charles City County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Charles City County (Va.) under various accession numbers.
Biographical Information
Charles City County was named for Charles I of England and was one of the eight shires established in 1634. Its area is 204 square miles, and the county seat is Charles City.
Records have been destroyed at various times. The most damage occurred during the Civil War when the records were strewn through the woods in a rainstorm. A few pre-Civil War volumes such as deed books, will books, minute books, and order books exist.
Scope and Content
Charles City County (Va.) Records, 1641-1901, includes miscellaneous records from the following series: Court Records, Tax and Fiscal Records, Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Marriage/Vital Statistics, Fiduciary Records, Military/Pension Records, Land Records, Justice of the Peace Records, County Administrative Records, Health and Medical Records, School Records, Wills, and Election Records.
Conservation of pages from 1682 and 1689-1690 were partially funded by the Order of Descendants of Colonial Cavaliers through the Library of Virginia Foundation's Adopt Virginia History Program.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Charles City County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
See the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
For more information and a listing of lost records localities see Lost Records research note.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Charles City County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--Charles City County.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Charles City County.
Contents List
- Land Tax Books, Warrants, and Executions Index, 1760-1851
  Land Tax Books, 1812-1813; Warrants, 1760-1820; Executions Index, 1831-1851.
- Wills, Bonds, and Court Records, 1642, 1682
  Court Records, 1642; Order Book, pages 139-140, 1682. Photocopies.
- Records, 1682-1893
  Will of Barnard Major, 3 September 1777; Deeds and Wills, pages 471-474, 1766; Deeds and Wills, pages 77-90, 1689-1690; Wills and Deeds, 1682; Affidavits to be attached to insolvent capitation and property lists, 1893; Deed of Robert Pearman to Thomas W. Tyler, 1845; Decree in Jones vs. Heirs of Jones, undated; Subpoena Docket, 1861-1868.
- Deeds, Wills, etc., 1724-1731
  Deeds, Will, and miscellaneous records.
- Replevin Bonds and Ended Causes, 1760-1800
  Replevin Bonds, 1760-1771, and Ended Causes, 1780-1800.
- Records, 1810-1896
  Court Records re: water rights, fishing rights, mills, estrays, etc., 1820-1880; Delinquent Lists, Improper Assesments, and Licenses, 1810-1890; Lists of Deaths, 1865-1896; Lunacy Papers, 1853-1895.
- Records, 1800-1900
  Promissory Notes, 1800-1899; Papers and Accounts, circa 1820-1890; School Records, circa 1900; Birth Lists, 1892-1896.
- Records, 1752-1896
  Summonses, 1855-1896; Military and Pension Records, 1832-1880; Loyalty Oaths, 1866-1883; Promissory Notes, 1752-1799; Deeds, 1759-1895.
- Records, 1782-1894
  Estate Papers (Wills), 1782-1893; Jury Lists and Summons, 1854-1894.
- Records, 1783-1896
  Treasurer Papers, 1871-1890; Election Lists and Returns, 1795-1896; Administrators Accounts and Bonds, 1783-1887.
- Records, 1760-1897
  Reports of Food and Salt Agents, 1862-1864; Clerk's Records, 1788-1889; Commissioner of Revenue Records, 1831-1878; County Assessor Records, 1870-1884; Sheriff's Records, 1760-1896; Court Records, 1852-1897; Justice of the Peace Records, 1827-1892; Overseers of the Poor Records, 1816-1894; Road and Bridge Records, 1853-1896.
- Records, 1757-1897
  Delinquent Lands, 1850-1880; Correspondence, Insurance Policies, etc., circa 1830-1890; Index to Cases, 1757-1897.
- Order Book and Deed, 1698-1723
  Order Book, 1722-1723; Deed, 1698.